Eugene A. Turner Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Eugene A. Turner Papers
1824-1948
1913-1948
RG 206
Yale University Divinity School Library
2
(5 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, and collected material document the life and work of Eugene A. Turner, who served under the YMCA in China from 1913 to 1947. Turner was involved in student and city work for the Y.M.C.A. in China and was a keen observer of Chinese customs and political events.
Turner, Eugene Alfred
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nancy Turner Parlette, 2006
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1914-1948
II. Writings and Notes, 1913-1948, no date
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1929-1943, no date
IV. Collected Material, 1824-1937, no date
Biographical / Historical
Eugene A. Turner was born in Wake Forest, North Carolina. He had completed a Bachelor's Degree, Master's Degree, and Law Degree at Wake Forest College by 1906. After a year of teaching at a preparatory school, Turner became Y.M.C.A. Secretary at the Georgia School of Technology. In 1913 Turner went to China under the Y.M.C.A. and worked with students in the city of Hangchow. According to a biographical sketch, Turner "built up a Y.M.C.A. which, in a short time, enlisted the support of government officials and the literati. He also helped to train an efficient staff of Chinese to whom he relinquished the executive work, remaining as an advisor. He organized, coached and conducted the first inter-scholastic football league ever attempted in Hangchow. Other activities were pioneered: debates, oratorical contests, essay contests, etc. He organized Bible study groups among the students." After a furlough, Turner returned to China in 1928 and was sent to Wuchang and served as Y.M.C.A. General Secretary. He later served in Nanchang, home of the New Life Movement and had personal contact with General and Madame Chiang Kai-shek. Turner was a leader in the Christian Rehabilitation Center in Kiangsi Province, which was involved in the rehabilitation of districts previously held by Communist forces. Turner was married to Mary Effie Lee Turner and was the father of Frank Turner and Eugene Alfred Turner, Jr., who was also involved in Y.M.C.A. work.
Scope and Contents
The Eugene A. Turner Papers complement other collections of China Y.M.CA. workers held at the Divinity School Library, including the papers of Lyman Hoover, Dwight W.Edwards, Lennig Sweet, and Austin Long, as well as China Y.M.C.A. records in the archives of the World Student Christian Federation.
The majority of the family correspondence is from the war years when Eugene Turner was separated from his wife and children. General correspondence includes letters to and from Madame Chiang Kai-shek, as well as Y.M.C.A. colleagues. The reports from China in Series II are excellent substantive reports of Turner's work with the Y.M.C.A. dating from 1913 to 1947. He also comments on political events and describes Chinese customs. The documentation of these reports is supplemented by writings in Series III.
Missions -- China; Missionaries; Young Men's Christian Associations of China
- Correspondence, 1914-1948; Series I
  - Family Correspondence
    - Letters to/from Eugene and Mary
      - From Hangchow, 1937 Nov-1939 Mar (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - From Tsingtao-Chengtu-Chungking, Kunming, 1940 Jan- 1941 Mar (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Kweiyong-Kanshein-atsea-Calcutta, 1941 Apr- 1942 Dec (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - From Calcutta- with Armed Forces, 1943 Jan- 1943 Mar (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - With Armed Forces: China, Burma, India, 1943 Apr- 1943 May (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - With Armed Forces: China, Burma, India, 1943 Jun-Jul (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - With Armed Forces: China, Burma, India, 1943 Aug-Sep (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - With Armed Forces, Kunming, 1945 Sep- Oct (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - With Armed Forces, US Consulate, 1945 Nov (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - From Chungking-Shanghai, 1945 Dec (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - From Wuchong, Hankow, 1946 Jan (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - From Hankow, 1946 Feb (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - From Hankow, 1946 Mar- Apr (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - From Hankow-Kiun Kiang-Nanchang, 1946 May- Jun (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - From Hankow-Shanghai, 1946 Jul (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Letters to/from sons
      - From Hangchow-Shanghai, 1935 May 1937 Oct-Dec (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - From Hangchow-Shanghai, 1938 Jan (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - From Hangchow-Shanghai, 1938 Feb-Apr (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - From Shanghai-Hangchow, 1938 May-Aug (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - From Shanghai-Hangchow, 1938 Sep-Dec (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - From Tsingtao-Kaifeng-Shanghai, 1939 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - From Shanghai-Tsingtao, 1940 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - From Hangchung-Chengtu-Kunming, Calcutta- Sons in US, Mrs. Tryon, NC, 1941 Jan- 1943 Sep (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - From Eugene Jr.-Marine Corps. Chaplin- China, 1945 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - From Tryon, NC-, Eugene Turner, Jr. China, NJ, 1946 Jan-Jul (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Letters to Aunt Effie
      - From Shanghai, Calcutta, 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - General Correspondence
    - Letters of Eugene Turner to/from others
      - To/from Mary Connally, several from Frank Lenz, Educational Secretary of the YMCA, 1914 -1927 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Several from A. Wayne Hanson, 1929-1931 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - From Eugene Barnett, Herschleb, 1932 Jun- Dec (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - From Herschleb, Barnett, to Chairman and Madame Chiang Kai-Shek, 1933-1937 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - From Barnett- to Madame Chiang, 1938 Jan-Sep (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - From "Sister Mary", Barnett, Madame Chiang, 1939 Feb-1941 Jul (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - Some re. stamp collecting, Hugh Hubbard, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - From Jay Oliver- incl. letter of Eugene, Jr to Oliver also, 1945-1948, 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Letters to/from Dwight Edwards, 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence of others
      - Includes description of fall of Nanking by George Fitch, 1915,1931-1948 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Letter fragments, no date (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Writings and notes, 1913-1948; Series II
  - EAT reports from Hangchow, including description of life in city, address by Governor at opening of Y.M.C.A, Sherwood Eddy campaign (1914), athletic and educational work, political unrest, 1913-1916 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - EAT reports from Hangchow and Shanghai, including re. Y.M.C.A. membership campaign, travels throughout China, patriotic demonstrations, 1917-1920 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - EAT reports from Hangchow, including re. World Student Christian Federation meeting in Peking, political unrest, campaign of popular education, 1922-1924 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - EAT reports from Hangchow and Wuchang, including re. Chinese customs, burning of the kitchen god, Y.M.C.A. membership campaign, "popular education in the meaning of citizenship"; move from student work to city work, 1925-1928 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - EAT reports from Wuchang, including re. membership campaign, Feng Yu-shiang the Christian General, civil war, visit of Dr. Kirby Page, 1929-1931 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - EAT reports from Wuchang, Kuling, Tryon NC, including regarding flood relief, Japanese troops, return home due to Y.M.C.A. financial situation, engagement as teacher of English Literature at Central China College, Wuchang, return to Y.M.C.A. work, New Life Movement; appointment as Regional Secretary for Shantung, 1932-1938 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - EAT reports from Tsingtao, Hankow, and elsewhere in China; war rehabilitation work, retirement, 1939-1947 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Annual reports of EAT from Hangchow and Shanghai, 1914-1919 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Articles by EAT, including "Injecting leaven into the lump", 1922,1923, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Articles by EAD, including regarding Japanese occupation of Hangchow, "Some reasons for disturbed conditions in China," "Life sketch of Wen Shih-Tsen", 1938, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Notes of EAD: textiles in China, for talks, sermons, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Writings of others: "Report on China situation," "The Bible marches on," "A new variety of 1905", report on work of Euguene A. Turner, Jr. for Home Missions Council of North America, 1941-1943, no date (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Broadcast bulletins: China, 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - NCCC bulletins, 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Regarding Y.M.C.A.: broadcasts, newsletters, report letters of S.C. Leung, Lyman Hoover, 1938-1948 (Box 4, Folder 52)
- Personal items and memorabilia, 1929-1943; Series III
  - Biographical sketch, photographs, passports and health certificate, financial records, tribute, 1932-1941, no date (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Information regarding stamp collecting, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Newsclippings regarding E.T., 1929-1943 (Box 4, Folder 55)
- Collected material, 1824-1937; Series IV
  - Misc. photos and newsclippings, 1937, no date (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Chinese language items, No date (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Chinese language items, No date (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Church bulletins, programs, poems, 1920-1946 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Booklets, articles including "An Outline of the Organization of the Kuomintang and the Chinese Government", "Bulltown" newspaper for American troops in China and India, "A Letter from Madame Chiang Kai-shek to Boys and Girls Across the Ocean", 1940-1943,no date (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Postcards, money, miscellaneous, 1940, no date (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Leaflets regarding YMCA, No date (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Typescript copy of journal of Elisha Loomis, who was among the first company of missionaries to Hawaii; journal documents Loomis's tour of Hawaii in 1824-1826 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - "Shanghai's Schemozzle" (reprinted cartoons and "In Parenthesis" observations from North China Daily News), 1937 (Box 5, Folder 64)